<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The designe of God in the saints, or, The spirit transporting the minde of a Christian from the humane nature into the divine in the carrying on of which designe, the saint is a meere passive / by George Hassal.</title>
            <author>Hassal, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25419</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08951703</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08951703</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42081</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43072)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42081)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1286:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The designe of God in the saints, or, The spirit transporting the minde of a Christian from the humane nature into the divine in the carrying on of which designe, the saint is a meere passive / by George Hassal.</title>
                  <author>Hassal, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sanctification.</term>
               <term>Holiness.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42081:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42081:1"/>
            <p>THE DESIGNE OF GOD In the SAINTS: <hi>OR,</hi> The Spirit tranſporting the minde of a Chriſtian from the humane Nature into the divine.</p>
            <p>In the carrying on of which Deſigne, the Saint is a meere paſſive.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Haſſal,</hi> a member of the Army.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zechariah the 4.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe the 6.<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Then he anſwered and ſpake unto me, ſaying, this is the word of the Lord unto <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> ſaying, not by might, nor by power, but by my ſpirit, ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42081:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42081:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know, that in the ſetting forth but of theſe few lines, I ſhall be brought under the cenſure of two ſorts of men; the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and ſpirituall; as for the naturall man, I look not upon him as a competent Judge here, for he knowes not the things of the Spirit, neither can he, for they are ſpiritually diſcerned, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how can he judge of thoſe things he is ignorant of; yet I am ſure I ſhall not eſcape his cenſure however; but bleſſed be the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he hath taught me how to beare the hard cenſures, reproaches, and revilings of
<pb facs="tcp:42081:3"/>ſuch men with patience, whil'ſt I look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen; for the things that are ſeene are temporary, but the things that are not ſeen are eternall; But as for the ſpirituall man, he knoweth all things that appertaineth to life, and godlineſſe; The ſpirit ſearcheth the deep things of God, and revealeth it unto him: ſo that he is a competent Judge, Judging all things, yet he himſelfe is judged of no man; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am ſure of his charitable cenſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he can tell how to judge ſpiritually.</p>
            <p>Now Gentle Reader, which of theſe two thou art, I doe not know; but this I ſhall deſire to certifie thee of, that I doe not write this, to teach thee of the Father, as to ſay, know him, for that is the work of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; nor to enlighten thy underſtanding, for the Lord hath prepared a Lamp for his anointed, even Ieſus Chriſt, the true light, that lightneth every man that commeth into the world; but if this may be to thee as an evidence to theſe truths, as already mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in thee, I ſhall much rejoyce, and ſo I believe thou wilt; for, from that ſhort
<pb facs="tcp:42081:3"/>(yet ſweet) experience that I have had of the Spirit, I finde it to be the nature of the Saints, (in whom it is) to rejoyce in one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others light, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, in <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> the <hi>13.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe</hi> the <hi>9.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> The light of the righteous rejoyceth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but the lamp of the wicked ſhall be put out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Saint who is truly ſpiritualized, is (as it were) overwhelmed with extreme paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Love, Ioy, and ſpirituall delight in beholding the ſame light in others, that is in himſelfe; wherefore, as the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> then bare record of Chriſt comming in the fleſh, and being made manifeſt in the fleſh; ſo doe I now bare record of his coming in the Spirit, in the fleſh of the Saints, and manifeſting himſelfe unto them; and that, as the fleſh of Chriſt died at Ieruſalem, and roſe againe; ſo doth the fleſh of a Saint (when Chriſt comes) dye to the old Adam, and (by the power of the reſurrection of Chriſt) live to the new Adam, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the mind; the Saint being once clothed with Chriſt (which is his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe) Mortality (that came by the fall of the firſt Adam) is ſwallowed up of life,
<pb facs="tcp:42081:4"/>which is the ſecond Adam; and ſo Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader, this is my earneſt deſire, that we may waite upon God for a further Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of himſelfe, untill he ſhall renew our ſtrength; then ſhall wee mount up with wings as Eagles; then ſhall we runne, and not be weary, we ſhall walke, and not faint, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the <hi>40.31.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Bwels of love, GEORGE HASSALL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42081:4"/>
            <head>THE DESIGNE OF GOD IN THE SAINTS; <hi>OR,</hi> The Spirit tranſporting the minde of a Chriſtian from the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into the Divine.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat (which according to my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the Spirit of God) I perceive to be his deſigne in every one of thoſe he intends to manifeſt himſelfe unto (but are yet in this veile of fleſh) is, to tranſport them from fleſh to Spirit, from fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where they are in bondage, to the ſpirituall <hi>Canaan,</hi> where he will make them free; from <hi>Babylon</hi> in the Myſterie, where they are in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42081:5"/>Captivity, unto <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in the Myſterie, where they ſhall be free Denizens; from the beauty and excellency of a fleſhly creature, to the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and excellency of the ſpirituall Creator; from all worldly glory, and honour whatſoever, to that heavenly honour, and glorious pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, to be the ſonnes of God, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires with Chriſt; <hi>(In whoſe preſence is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of joy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore;) from the power of darkneſſ unto his marvellous light;</hi> from all outward, or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary worſhips, formes, and carnall Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, to worſhip him who is the true God, only in Spirit and truth: in a word, it is to tranſport the mind of a Chriſtian, or rather the mind, which is the Chriſtian (when ſpiritualiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) from the humane nature of fleſh, to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature of Spirit; as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Though we have knowne Chriſt in the fleſh, yeet henceforth know we him ſo no more, but in Spirit.</hi> And ſo the Saint will ſay, (when he is got once to live with Chriſt in Spirit;) I knew Chriſt (as I thought) once in thoſe fleſhly diſpenſations (or outward meanes, as ſome call them) but hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth I ſhall deſire to know him no more ſo but in Spirit, as I doe. The Saint being baptized with that one Baptiſme <hi>(not the putting away the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God)</hi> by the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, (<hi>Peter</hi> the firſt, the third, and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42081:5"/>21.) knowes Chriſt to be in him, that heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Manna, the bread of life,</hi> and to be in him <hi>a Vine yielding fruit,</hi> and to be in him <hi>a well of water</hi> ſpringing up unto <hi>eternall life; Paul</hi> ſaith, that in the miniſtration of bread and wine, they did but hold forth the Lords death till he came; <hi>And when Chriſt, which was the ſubſtance, was come, then the ſhadow was to be done away;</hi> they were not to retaine the ſhadow with the ſubſtance, and therefore ſayes the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Coloſſians</hi> the 2.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> and the 16. <hi>Let no man therefore judge you in meat, or in drinke, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the new Moone, or of the Sabbath dayes: which are a ſhadow of things to come, but the body is of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When a man is new borne of the Spirit, he is then a new bottle, a veſſell of honour fit for his maſters uſe. Now ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Men doe not put old wine into new bottles, but new wine into new bottles, and both are preſerved;</hi> New ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall wine is moſt fit for that Saint that is new ſpiritualiz'd. <hi>Wherefore, if</hi> he <hi>be dead with Chriſt from the</hi> rudiments <hi>of the world, why as though living in the world,</hi> ſhould he be ſubject to ordinances, as the Apoſtle ſaith in <hi>Coloſſians</hi> the 2.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> and the 20.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and in <hi>Galathians</hi> the 4.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> he ſaith to them, <hi>But now after ye have known God, or rather are known of God; how turne yee againe to the weak and beggerly elements where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye deſire againe to be in bondage.</hi> As if
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42081:6"/>he ſhould ſay, in that Chapter, as long as ye were under that low diſpenſation of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, ye were but (as ſervants) under Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Governours; but now is the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time of the Father come to make you free, and therefore he hath ſent forth his Spirit of Adoption into your hearts, whereby you crie <hi>Abba, Father;</hi> and now that you are no more ſervants but ſonnes, why doe you not keep you ſo? Why doe you look back upon thoſe world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elements, as if you had a deſire to be againe in bondage to them.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in the ſame Chapter confeſſeth, that his firſt coming unto them, and preaching of the Goſpel, was through infirmitie of the fleſh; (being then under a low fleſhly diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation) and yet they deſpiſed him, not, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him, as if he had been Chriſt himſelfe; but now that he comes to preach unto them, in a miniſtration above Ordinances, a diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spirit, by which they ſhould bee made free (poore man!) he is become their enemie, as he there complaines. But why <hi>Paul</hi> art thou become their enemy now, that not long ſince waſt ſo great in their books? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I endeavour to draw them off from fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordinances, and the Elements of the world, (that by nature are no Gods) by preaching unto them the myſterie of godlineſſe; Chriſt manifeſt in the fleſh, not only Chriſt which is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42081:6"/>dead, but rather Chriſt which is riſen in us, the hope of glory; but they are ſo faſt glewed to their formes, that they cannot endure ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and therefore they look upon me as their enemie. Thus is <hi>Paul</hi> lookt upon as an enemy, (by thoſe that formerly would have pluckt out their eyes, and have given them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, to doe him good) becauſe he tells them the truth, and came not unto them in the ſame miniſtration that he formerly came to them in, but in a higher and more ſpirituall; and yet ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> ſweetly to them in the 19. and 20. verſes, <hi>My little children, of whom I travaile againe in birth, untill Chriſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in you; I deſire to be preſent with you now, and to change my voyce, for I ſtand in doubt of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See now this bleſſed Apoſtle, after that Chriſt was formed in him, and that he was brought up to live in the third Heaven, in Spirit, how earneſt and deſirous is he to have all thoſe (that formerly he had ſociety with, and had preacht the Goſpell through infirmity unto) to have the like ſpirituall injoyment in them, and to be brought up to the ſame perfection and unity of the Spirit with himſelfe. Now that <hi>Paul</hi> was made a partaker of the divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turre, he could as well comprehend the Sea in the hollow of his hand, as conceale it; the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature is love; (God is love,) and here
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42081:7"/>you might ſee this nature in <hi>Paul;</hi> for after he knew the oneneſſe and unity of the Saints with the Father, he muſt make it knowne unto them, and yet they keep cloſe to their old formes, and will not heare him, becauſe they thinke he is fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er from his firſt principles, and is led away from his former profeſſion, with the errours of the wicked thinking it ſtrange, that whilſt they are in this veile of fleſh, they ſhould be ſo tranſlated into the Image of God, as to worſhip him in ſuch a ſpirituall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner above Ordinances; but here was the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them and <hi>Paul,</hi> Chriſt being formed in him, and manifeſted unto him, as the ſubſtance of all theſe ſhadowes; he did (by what he apprehended of him) ſee the vanity of the one, and the glory and excellency of the other; comparing ſpirituall things, with his ſpiricualized underſtanding; and therefore he ſaith, <hi>My little children, of whom Itravell in birth againe, untill Chriſt be formed in you. And know yee not, that except Chriſt be in you, yee are Reprobates.</hi> And in other place; <hi>Stand faſt in the Liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made you free, and be not entangled againe with the yoke of bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as the <hi>Jewes</hi> thought that Chriſt ſpake of the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that <hi>Solomon</hi> built, when he ſpake of his body; and as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> thought that Chriſt had ſpoken of a naturall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42081:7"/>birth, when he ſpake of a ſpirituall; ſo did theſe men unto whom <hi>Paul</hi> writ, (comparing ſpirituall things to their naturall and carnall underſtandings) thinke that he ſpake of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man, when he ſpake of the ſpirituall; they thought that he had ſpoken of naturall freedome, when indeed he ſpoke of a ſpirituall freedome, ſuch as he enjoyed when he was in the ſtocks, the enjoyment thereof being then ſo gladſome, ſo joyous and ſweet unto him, that it made him ſing for joy of heart; as God ſaith in the laſt of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> but one, when he was in bonds, he was yet free; and ſo ſhall all the Saints of God, whoſe lot and portion it is, or ſhall be, to be perſecuted for the teſtimony of Chriſt their head; Whoſoever believeth in him, ſhall not be aſhamed: the Father will uphold them with the right hand of his Righteouſneſſe. It is now the weakneſſe of many in our dayes to thinke, that becauſe they doe not apprehend God in themſelves, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is not in them, and becauſe that they are not able to comprehend the Father, that therefore he is not able to comprehend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in them; thinking, that he diſpences himſelfe unto his Saints while they are here, only by ſhadowes, and not in ſubſtance; by theſe outward meanes (as they call it) hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reading, and preaching, and Bread and Wine, and not in Spirit; when for my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42081:8"/>own part I finde it nothing ſo, as I muſt needs ſay: and if you ſhall ask me what comfort I had, or ſupportance, when I was under thoſe Adminiſtrations; truly I muſt needs confeſſe, I then thought that my greateſt comfort in this world, was in thoſe ordinances; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I now finde, (as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid) that of a truth it was God within me that ſupported and conforted me, and I knew it not, becauſe I did not then apprehend him; the appointed time of the Father was not come to make me free, and while I was a ſervant, it was not meet that I ſhould know what my Lord did; but (now bleſſed for ever be his name) I have heard his ſweet ſtill voice within me, ſaying, <hi>Henceforth call I thee no more a ſervant, but my friend; the ſervant knoweth not what his Lord doth, but all that I have heard of the Father will I declare unto thee.</hi> It is now my work in thee to diſpell thoſe clouds of fleſhly luſts, that have a long time harboured in thee, and been the veile that hath all this time hindred thee from behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my glory in ſpirit; I am the new <hi>Adam,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Adam, I will ſit in thee as a refiners fire, &amp; as fullers ſope; I will take away all thy droſſe and tin. Loe, I create a new heaven, and a new earth in thee, and the firſt heaven, and the firſt earth ſhall paſſe away;</hi> The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> with all his glory and ſplendor, which hath hitherto been thy heaven, it ſhall vaniſh away; and the ſecond
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42081:8"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> (which after God is <hi>created in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and true holineſſe</hi>) muſt take place; and in that new heaven, and new earth that I create in thee, there ſhall dwell Righteouſneſſe; It is I friend, that am that righteouſneſſe, that will dwell in thee, and make mine abode with thee; nay, I will ſup with thee, and thou ſhalt ſup with me, and I will impart of the divine nature un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee; <hi>As the Father hath given to me of the Spirit freely, ſo will I give unto thee,</hi> and thou ſhalt partake thereof; thou ſhalt ſee thy ſelfe to live in, and by me, thou ſhalt ſee thy ſelfe to have thy being and ſpirituall ſubſiſtence in me, <hi>I am that bread of life, and that water of life; our of thy belly ſhall flow rivers of living water. I will deſtroy in thee every evill thought, and high imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that exalteth in ſelfe againſt me;</hi> for now is the judgement of this world in thee, now ſhall the Prince of this world be caſt out, <hi>ſinne ſhall have no more dominion over thee;</hi> for I will ſo manifeſt my ſelfe unto thee, that thou ſhalt no more luſt after, nor be in love with any thing below me; as thou ſhalt apprehend me in Spirit, all thy legall Righteouſneſſe ſhall appeare to thee but as a menſtruous rag, and therefore wait thou upon me, untill I accompliſh this my work in thee: for in the doing of it thou ſhalt be a meere paſſive, but when it is finiſht, that I have once tranſlated thee into my Image, the ſhalt thou bring forth fruit, ſuitable to the ſtock you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42081:9"/>are graffed into; yea, thou ſhalt be ſo clothed with fine linnen, clean and white, that thou ſhalt not in the leaſt be found naked. Mortality ſhall be ſwallowed up of life; and thou ſhalt give thanks unto him, <hi>who hath given thee the victory through thy Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it is my meat and drinke to doe the will of my father, ſo ſhall it be thine: for I will tranſport thy minde, thy heart, and affections from all earthly things whatſoever (though it have appeared unto thee formerly never ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,) unto heavenly, divine, and ſpirituall things, that ſhall never vaniſh away; it ſhall be more glorious, <hi>yea, more ſweet unto thy taſte then the hony or the hony combe; it ſhall be more precious unto thee then the gold of Ophir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed be the Lord, I finde that he hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (in ſome meaſure) ſo taken me up above fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and carnall things, that I only wait upon him for a further and fuller manifeſtation of himſelf in me, according to his promiſe; for I know that the Lord is not ſlack concerning his promiſe, as ſome men count ſlackneſſe; I know that his <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing draweth nigh; he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry;</hi> and though that in outward ordinances, I was once buſie and active, yet I finde that in the inward and ſpirituall work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings within me, I was then (yea and am ſtill) a meere paſſive; and therefore (according to my apprehenſion) we muſt know, that in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42081:9"/>of a Chriſtian, out of the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into the divine, he is a meere paſſive, and not active at all, untill he partake of the divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and then, as it is the divine nature of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to be active in ſearching the deep things of God, and declaring it to him, ſo is it a divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the Spirit (likewiſe) to make the minde active in ſpirituall things, and in declaring unto others, what God hath manifeſted of himſelfe in him; <hi>That as the Father is, ſo is he in this preſent world,</hi> the 1. of <hi>John</hi> the 4.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and the 17.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> but this we are not able to apprehend whilſt we are in the body, being abſent from the Lord, or whilſt we are in low fleſhly diſpenſations, being abſent from the ſpiritual, which is beyond humane ſenſe, or common reaſon; <hi>For as is the earthy, ſuch are they that are earthy, and as is the heavenly, ſuch are they that are heavenly:</hi> when we are once tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into his heavenly Image, <hi>then we ſhall ſee as we are ſeen, and know as we are known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as he is perfect, ſo are we, with one and the ſame perfection; and as he is holy, ſo are we, with one and the ſame holineſſe; and as he is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo are we, with one and the ſame righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; Chriſt is the Lord our righteouſneſſe, as well as the Fathers; (only we want a fuller manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, which we muſt waite for) he is that lamp that the Father hath prepared for his Anointed, <hi>to be a Lanthorne unto their feet, and a light unto their pathes;</hi> whilſt we are in the humane and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42081:10"/>naturall condition, there is a ſtrong man armed (which is our luſts, armed with a deſire of worldly riches, honour, and pleaſures,) keepeth the houſe (which is the minde) and for a while the things that he enjoyeth are in peace, <hi>untill the ſtronger then he cometh</hi> (which is Chriſt) and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſeth him of the minde (taking it off from doting on the world) and taketh poſſeſſion him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and maketh it his <hi>Temple,</hi> his <hi>houſe of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and whips out all the buyers and ſellers out of it;</hi> he will no longer ſuffer <hi>a den of theeves</hi> to harbour there, but takes it up for his owne habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and there he ſits, <hi>as a Refiners fire, and as Fullers ſope,</hi> purifying, &amp; cleanſing us as gold, and ſilver, that we may offer unto the Lord, an offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Righteouſneſſe, in all which the Creature is a meere paſſive ſtill; <hi>Chriſt alone, who is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Councel, and excellent in working; his arme alone brings ſalvation to him, and his righteouſneſſe it ſuſtaineth him;</hi> and therefore ſayes the Saints, <hi>this is the Lords doing, and it is wonderfull in our eyes;</hi> So that I ſay, the Chriſtian in the various workings of God in him (which is the drawing him up, from one diſpenſation which is low, unto another, that is higher, and ſo from one diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to another, untill he take him up above all, to live in Spirit with himſelfe) doth not in the leaſt, help, or aſſiſt, but is a meere paſſive in it, though he think himſelf active in it, by following of good duties, which is only bodily exerciſe, <hi>and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42081:10"/>profiteth little,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith: but being once brought up into the nature of Spirit, he is then active in ſpirituall exerciſes; all his ſacrifices that he offers to the Father are ſpirituall, he can offer no other; and ſuch only are well pleaſing to the Father, as are offered in the Son, <hi>For in him alone he is well pleaſed.</hi> God accepts not of any duty, or performance whatſoever, though never ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that is not done, and acted in, and by Chriſt himſelfe, to the Father, from the new Creature, which in us is <hi>borne of the free-woman,</hi> and not of the <hi>bond-woman;</hi> of the Spirit, and not of the fleſh; as Chriſt himſelf ſaid, that <hi>God is a Spirit;</hi> ſo he ſaid, that <hi>they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in truth,</hi> which is Chriſt himſelf. <hi>He is the way, the truth and the life; In him we live, move, and have our being;</hi> in him we are active, and, <hi>except we abide in him we can doe nothing;</hi> as he ſaith in <hi>John</hi> the 15. <hi>ver.</hi> the 5.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>I am the vine, ye are the branches, he that abideth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth much fruit; for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me ye can doe nothing;</hi> So that when a man is borne again, when he is brought up to live with Chriſt, in the unity and oneneſſe of that ever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit of himſelfe, he is then active, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth much fruit: <hi>he is then no more a ſervant,</hi> (as he was before) <hi>but a friend, The ſervant</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>knoweth not what his Lord doth, but I have called you friends: for all things that I have heard of my Father, I have made known unto you.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:42081:11"/>He keeps nothing back from the Saints, becauſe they are his friends: and <hi>he hath choſen them,</hi> and ordained them, that they ſhould bring forth fruit, and that their fruit ſhall remaine, ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the firſt of the <hi>Corinths,</hi> and the laſt ver. <hi>But we all with open face, beholding as in a glaſſe the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image from glory to glory, even as by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord;</hi> Where you may take notice, that this change in a Chriſtian is wrought by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: this Spirit as a glaſſe, is that, in which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the glory of the Lord; at the ſight of which precious and beautifull aſpect, we are ſo enamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewith, that there is a preſent change wrought in us; our mindes and affections are by the Spirit tranſported from all the glory, beauty, and excellency of the old Creation (that is under the Sun, (that as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid) we behold them all to be but <hi>vanity and vexation of Spirit</hi>) unto the glory, beauty, and excellency of the new Creation, which is above the naturall Sun; <hi>even Righteouſneſſe, and peace, and Joy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi> A Saint having no ſooner <hi>found this one Pearle of ſo great price, but he goeth preſently, and ſels all that he hath, and buyes it;</hi> when he is once borne of water, which is the Spirit, ſuch is the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full operation of it, that it worketh a Saint into its own nature, as fire is ſaid to do wood; The law of this Spirit of life, is that <hi>which frees us from the Law of ſin and death,</hi> it makes us free of that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42081:11"/>the <hi>new Jeruſalem that comes down from God out of heaven,</hi> and indeed is in all the Saints, and the Saints in it, that live in this Spirit; they have no need of the light of the Sun, nor the light of the Moone; (which is the light of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and his glory) but the Lord God ſhall enlighten them, and the Lamb ſhall be their light, which is the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and his glory: for as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was a type or ſhadow of the ſecond; ſo all thoſe Types, and Ordinances, and the Law in the letter (as given in <hi>Moſes</hi> Adminiſtration) though the very light and glory of the firſt <hi>Adam, (by which we only know good and evill)</hi> yet, but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the light and glory of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> by which <hi>we not only know the will of God,</hi> but are happy in <hi>doing of it;</hi> The old man <hi>knows his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will, but doth it not,</hi> becauſe he is weak; but the <hi>new man,</hi> he is ſtrong, it is his meat and drink <hi>to doe the will of his Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Saint doth come to behold the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God in Spirit, to enlighten him, and the Lamb to be his light, by which he ſeeth his unity and oneneſs with the Father, and the Son he then comes to the true knowledge of the Son of God, <hi>and growes up to a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt,</hi> as it is in <hi>Epheſians</hi> the 4. and the 12. ſo that when the Saints come to have the enjoyment of that ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting light ſpoken of in the 60.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Iſaiah, They ſhall be ſo rooted and grounded in him, that they ſhall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42081:12"/>not be toſſed to and fro with every winde of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftines, whereby they lye in waite to deceive men,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid Chriſt, <hi>If it were poſſible, they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the very elect:</hi> but the Saints ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once the enjoyment of this light, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that ever they ſhould be deceived; <hi>for they are borne of the Spirit, and are Spirit; now the ſpirituall man judgeth all things, yet he himſelfe is judged of no man;</hi> he cannot be ſeduc'd by falſe Prophets, that ſhall ſay, loe, Chriſt is in this forme, and loe, Chriſt is in that forme; he believes them not, becauſe the Son of Righteouſneſſe is already riſen in him, with healing under his wings; the <hi>Day-ſtar,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, is ariſen in him; Chriſt will in no wiſe ſuffer the wicked one to touch him: <hi>For he hath deſired him for his habitation,</hi> Pſal. 132. ver. the 13. and there he dwels, and keeps poſſeſſion in him, and where is a ſtronger then he to turne him out? <hi>Shall the gates of Hell prevaile againſt him?</hi> no, nor the <hi>Dragon</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; our <hi>Michael</hi> will take a courſe to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw them, and leave of them, neither <hi>root,</hi> nor <hi>branch</hi> in the Saint, but <hi>will keep him as the apple of his eye, which cannot behold iniquity.</hi> Marke what Chriſt ſaith (in the 60. of <hi>Iſa.</hi> and verſe 17.) unto the Saints, or the Church, <hi>For braſſe I will bring gold, and for iron I will bring ſilver, and for wood braſſe, and for ſtones iron: I will alſo make thy officers peace, and thine exactors Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42081:12"/>What a ſweet promiſe is here of Chriſt, with ſome expreſſions which hold forth to us his more excellent and exceeding glory in coming, then in the coming of the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> did the firſt man bring braſſe with him? why, Chriſt will bring for that gold; did the firſt man bring a fleſhly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration? 06 why, the ſecond <hi>man is the Lord from Heaven, heavenly;</hi> he will bring a more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and ſpirituall adminiſtration to the Saint, when he manifeſteth himſelfe unto him.</p>
            <p>But leaſt I ſhould here be miſtaken, I deſire the Reader to take notice, that what I call the Saint, or Chriſtian, is not menat by me, man, as he is by nature viſible to the naturall eye; but that which I call the Saint, is the minde of a man, tranſlated by the Spirit into the Image of God, or taken off from the fleſhly glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of creature, to look upon, and affect the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual glory of the Creator, as is before expreſſed; that is it which I call the Saint: for ſaith <hi>Paul, I thanke God, that with my minde I ſerve God, though with the fleſh I ſerve ſinne:</hi> the minde ſanctified is the Saint, and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> was a Saint, and ſo the minde being taken up by Chriſt from the humane nature of fleſh, into the divine nature of Spirit, and tranſlated into his Image or likeneſſe, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſaid to be a Chriſtian, or new creature; ſo that there is a clear difference between the law of the members (in ſuch a man) and the law of his mind, <hi>for the law of his member,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42081:13"/>alwayes warring, and rebelling againſt the law of his mind,</hi> &amp; is what w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſometime carries him away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to ſin: Wherefore it is not the might of the Presbyter, nor the power of the Magiſtrate, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in conſtraining, or in reſtraining, that can make a Saint; it is not their forms and ordinances that can any more bring a man to the ſpirituall <hi>Canaan,</hi> then <hi>Moſes</hi> could bring the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the temporall <hi>Canaan,</hi> he muſt be dead before they come there; it is not all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the world that can tranſport the minde of a man from the humane nature into the divine, (till when, he is neither a Chriſtian, nor a Saint) but the Lord Jeſus Chriſt and the power of his might; it is the Spirit of the Lord of Hoſts that ſhall make the great Mountaine become a Plaine before <hi>Zerubbable,</hi> it is he that hath laid the foundation, and it is he that ſhall come and finiſh it; wherefore I ſhall conclude with that ſaying of <hi>James,</hi> in chapter the 5. verſe the 7. and 8. <hi>Be patient therefore brethren, to the coming of the Lord, Behold the husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it, untill he receive the early and latter raine; Be ye alſo patient, ſtabliſh your hearts, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord draweth nigh.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42081:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
